[Music]
Reedman
reads The Giver by Lois Lowry narrated by Fraser Reedman chapter
[Music]
2 Jonas watched as his father poured a fresh cup of coffee. He waited. "You know,"
his father finally said, "every December was exciting to me when I
was young. And it has been for you and Lily, too, I'm sure. Each December brings such
changes." Jonas nodded. He could remember the Decembers back to when he had become,
well, probably a Four. The earlier ones were lost to him. But he observed them
each year, and he remembered Lily's earliest Decembers. He remembered when his family
received Lily, the day she was named, the day that she had become a One.
The Ceremony for the Ones was always noisy and fun. Each December, all the new
children born in the previous year turned One. One at a time— —there were
always 50 in each year's group, if none had been released— —they had been brought
to the stage by the Nurturers who had cared for them since
birth. Some were already walking, wobbly on their unsteady
legs; others were no more than a few days old, wrapped in blankets, held by their Nurturers.
"I enjoy the Naming," Jonas said. His mother agreed, smiling. "The year
we got Lily, we knew, of course, that we'd receive our female, because we'd made our
application and been approved. But I'd been wondering and wondering what her name would
be." "I could have sneaked a look at the list prior to the ceremony," Father
confided. "The committee always makes a list in advance, and it's right there in
the office at the Nurturing Center. "As a matter of fact," he went on, "I feel a
little guilty about this. But I did go in this afternoon and look to see if this
year's Naming list had been made yet was right there in the office, and I looked
up number 36 that's the little guy I've been concerned about CU it occurred to
me that it might enhance his nurturing if I could call him by a name. Just
privately, of course, when no one else was around." "Did you find it?" Jonas asked. He was
fascinated. It didn't seem a terribly important rule, but the fact that his
father had broken a rule at all aw him.
He glanced at his mother, the one responsible for adherence to the rules,
and was relieved that she was smiling. His father nodded. "His name— —if he
makes it to the Naming without being released, of course— —is to be
Gabriel. So I whisper that to him when I feed him every four hours, and during
exercise and playtime. If no one can hear me. "I call him Gabe, actually," he said, and
grinned. "Gabe jonis tried it out. A good name, he decided.
Though Jonas had only become a Five the year that they acquired Lily and learned
her name, he remembered the excitement conversations at home, wondering about
her: how would she look, who would she be, how she would fit into their established
family unit. He remembered climbing the steps to the stage with his parents, his
father by his side that year instead of with the Nurturers, since it was the year
that he would be given a new child of his own. He remembered his mother taking the
new child his sister, into her arms, while the document was read to the assembled family
units new child 23 the nameer had read.
"Lily." He remembered his father's look of delight, and that his father had
whispered, "She's one of my favorites. I was hoping for her to be the
one." The crowd had clapped, and Jonas had grinned. He liked his sister's name. Lily,
barely awake, had waved her small fist.
Then they had stepped down to make room for the next family unit. "When I was an
11 his father said now, "as you are, Jonas, I was very impatient, waiting for the
Ceremony of 12 It's a long two days. I remember that I enjoyed the Ones, as I
always do that I didn't pay much attention to the other ceremonies, except
for my sisters She became a Nine that year, and got her bicycle I've been
teaching her to ride mine, even though technically I wasn't supposed to
jonice laughed. It was one of the few rules that was not taken very seriously was almost always
broken. The children all received their bicycles at 9: they were not allowed to
ride bicycles before then. But almost always, the older brothers and sisters
had secretly taught the younger ones.
Jonas had been thinking already about teaching Lily. There was talk about changing the
rule in giving the bicycles at an earlier age. A committee was studying the
idea. When something went to a committee for study, the people always joked about
it. They said that the committee members would become Elders by the time the rule
change was made. Rules were very hard to change. Sometimes, if it was a very
important rule— —unlike the one governing the age for bicycles— —it would have to go,
eventually, to The Receiver for a decision. The Receiver was the most important
Elder. Jonas had never even seen him, that he knew of; someone in a position of such
importance lived and worked alone. But the committee would never
bother The Receiver with a question about bicycles; they would simply fret
and argue about it themselves for years, until the citizens forgot that it had
ever gone to them for study. His father continued. "So I watched and cheered when
my sister Kata became a Nine and removed her hair ribbons and got her bicycle,"
Father went on. "Then I didn't pay much attention to the T and 11s And finally
the end of the second day, which seemed
to go on forever, it was my turn. It was a Ceremony of 12 Jonas
shivered pictured his father must have been a shy and quiet boy, for he was a
shy and quiet man, seated with his group, waiting to be called to the
stage. The Ceremony of 12 was the last of the Ceremonies. The most
important. "I remember how proud my parents looked— —and my sister, too; even
though she wanted to be out riding the Bic publicly, she stopped fidgeting and
was very still and attentive when my turn came. "But to be honest, Jonas," his
father said, "for me there was not the element of suspense that there is with
your Ceremony cuz I was already fairly certain of what my Assignment was to be."
Jonas was surprised. There was no way, really, to know in advance. It was a
secret selection, made by the leaders of the community, the Committee of Elders,
who took the responsibility so seriously that there were never even any jokes made about
Assignments. His mother seemed surprised, too. "How could you have known?" she asked.
His father smiled his gentle smile. "Well, it was clear to me— —and my parents later
confessed that it had been obvious to them, too— —what my aptitude was I'd always
Lov the new children more than anything.
When my friends in my age group were holding bicycle races, or building toy
vehicles or bridges with their construction sets, or—" "All the things I do
with my friends," Jonas pointed out, and his mother nodded in agreement. "I always
participated, of course, because as children we must experience all of those
things. And I studied hard in school, as you do, Jonas. But again and again, during
free time, I found myself drawn to the new children I spent almost all of my
volunteer hours helping in the Nurturing Center. Of course the Elders knew that, from their
observation." Jonas nodded. During the past year he had been aware of the increasing level of
observation. In school, at recreation time, and during volunteer
hours, he had noticed the Elders watching him and the other Els He had seen them taking
notes. He knew, too, that the Elders were meeting for long hours all of the
instructors that he and the other Els had had during their years of school. "So
I expected it, and I was pleased, but not at all surprised, when my Assignment was
announced as Nurturer," Father explained. "Did everyone applaud, even
though they weren't surprised?" Jonas asked. "Oh, of course of course They were
happy for me, that my Assignment was what I wanted most. I felt very fortunate." His
father smiled. "Were any of the Els disappointed, your year?" Jonas asked.
Unlike his father, he had no idea what his Assignment would be. But he knew that
some would disappoint him. Though he respected his father's work, Nurturer
would not be his wish. And he didn't envy Laborers at all. His father thought. "No, I
don't think so. Of course the Elders are so careful in their observation and
selections." "I think it's probably the most important job in our community," his mother
commented. "My friend jika was surprised by her selection as Doctor," Father said,
"but she was thrilled. And let's see, there was Andre I remember that when we were
boys he never wanted to do physical things. He spent all the recreation time
he could with his construction set, and his volunteer hours were always on
building sites. The Elders knew that, of course course Andre was given the
Assignment of Engineer and he was delighted Andre later designed the
bridge that crosses the river to the west of town," Jonas's mother said. "It
wasn't there when we were children." "There are very rarely disappointments, Jonas. I
don't think you need to worry about that," his father reassured him. "And if there
are, you know there's an appeal process."
But they all laughed at that— —an appeal went to a committee for study. "I worry a
little about Asher's Assignment," Jonas confessed. "Asher's such fun. But he
doesn't really have any serious interests. He makes a game out of
everything." His father chuckled. "You know," he said, "I remember when Asher was a new
child at the Nurturing Center, before he was named. He never cried. He giggled and
laughed at everything. All of us on the staff enjoyed nurturing Asher." "The Elders
know Asher," his mother said. "They'll find exactly the right Assignment for him. I
don't think you need to worry about him.
But, Jonas, let me warn you about something that may not have occurred to
you. I know I didn't think about it until after my Ceremony of
12 What's that?" "Well, it's the last of the Ceremonies, as you
know. After 12 age isn't important. Most of us even lose track of how old we are
as time passes, though the information is in the Hall of Open Records, and we could
go and look it up if we wanted to. What's important is the preparation for adult
life, and the training you'll receive in your Assignment." "I know that Jonah said.
"Everyone knows that." "But it means," his mother went on,
"that you'll move into a new group. And each of your friends will. You'll no
longer be spending your time with your group of 11s After the Ceremony of 12 you'll be
with your Assignment group, with those in training. No more volunteer hours and
more recreation hours. So your friends will no longer be as close."
Jonas shook his head. "Asher and I will always be friends," he said firmly. "And
there will still be school." "That's true," his father agreed
what your mother said is true as well.
There will be changes." Good changes, though," his mother
pointed out. "After my Ceremony of 12 I missed my childhood recreation. But when
I entered my training for Law and Justice, I found myself with people who
shared my interests. I made friends on a new level, friends of all ages."
"Did you still play it all, after 12 Jonas asked. "Occasionally," his mother replied.
"But it didn't seem as important to me." "I did," his father said, laughing. "I
still do. Every day, at the Nurturing Center, I play bounce on the knee and
peek-aboo and hug the teddy He reached over and stroked
Jonas's neatly trimmed hair. "Fun doesn't end when you become
12 Lily appeared, wearing her night clothes in the doorway. She gave an
impatient sigh huh This is certainly a very long private conversation," she said.
"And there are certain people waiting for their comfort object." "Lily," her mother said fondly,
"you're very close to being an Eight, and when you're an Eight, your comfort object
will be taken away. It will be recycled to the younger children. You should be
starting to go off to sleep without it."
But her father had already gone to the shelf and taken down the stuffed elephant which was kept
there. Many of the comfort objects, like Lily were soft, stuffed, imaginary
creatures jonesis had been called a bear.
"Here you are Lily Billy he said. "I'll come help you remove your hair ribbons."
Jonas and his mother rolled their eyes, yet they watched affectionately as Lily
and her father headed to her sleeping room with a stuffed elephant that had
been given to her as a comfort object when she was
born. His mother moved to her big desk and opened her briefcase; her work never
seemed to end, even when she was at home in the evening. Jonas went to his own
desk and began to sort through his school papers for the evening's
assignment. But his mind was still on December and the coming
Ceremony. Though he had been reassured by the talk with his parents, he hadn't the
slightest idea what Assignment the Elders would be selecting for his future,
or how he might feel about it when the day came
[Music]